[Music]
so here is a value iteration
theorem
is
Plus
can you read all of
it I apologize I go lower down the board
my handwriting seriously deteriorates
but at which this condition in three is
met for all n greater than capital N
okay so Pi defined by step four is
Epsilon
optimal and VN + 1 minus V Star is less
than or equal to Epsilon by 2 when three
holds so when this holds VN + one is
Epsilon by 2 close to V
Star right so what is it A and B are
kind of easy we already seen that A and
B is essentially Barak theem right so
Barak fix Point theorem I'm sorry yeah
the Barak fix Point theem gives us A and
B correct what is the difference between
C and
D why do I have two of these
things don't they look
contradictory they look contradictory
not contradictory per say but
uh yeah
anyone anyone gives me the right answer
I'll give you a bonus Mark that
essentially means I've been following
whatever I've been saying so far so
probably you have to take down your role
number and note down
that now I got their
attention so people who don't know the
class averages for my quizzes tend to be
in like two or three out of 20
huh or 50 it doesn't matter what the
denominator is numerator doesn't seem to
change but so every Mark matters so tell
me what is the difference why do I need
c and
d
sorry it's Epsilon optimal Epsilon
optimal means it's close maybe I should
I say it in a different way
then you'll get it so what I'm saying is
that V Pi minus V Star is less than
Epsilon here I'm saying VN + 1 minus V
St is less than Epsilon by
2 remember my space V does not
necessarily contain only value functions
it's just a space of functions right VN
+ 1 need not be the value function
corresponding to the policy Pi even
though recover Pi by being greedy with
respect to VN + 1 does not mean if I
actually solve
for value of V Pi if I find V Pi it need
not be VN + one right so what three is
telling me is that V Pi is Epsilon what
C is telling me is V Pi is Epsilon
optimal what D is telling me is that VN
+ 1 is Epsilon by 2
optimal okay so prob they give me the
mark H I've never offered them
before right this this is an offer
nobody took it and it's easy enough
right all you need to do is just been
following the multiple times I kept
saying that V is not the space of value
functions the very beginning when
somebody said V is a space of value
function I corrected
you of this class very beginning of this
class anyway so let's look at the proofs
uh well A and B are immediate they
follow for benox fix Point theorem so
we'll start off with c and d
right
um
is
so just assume that three is met for
some some n okay so n is already met
that condition is been met right and
that V Pi the pi has been derived from
doing
this okay so Pi has been derived from
doing this and uh now I can use my
triangle inequality right it doesn't
matter that then this actually doesn't
matter right whether these conditions
are met or not I can take an arbitrary V
pi and a V Star and I can use a triangle
inequality and write this because it's
just about three points in space right
we talked about how I can keep using the
triangle inequality in an arbitrary
fashion because all I'm talking about
are just some three points in space
right so happens that one of them is V
Pi the other one is vn+ one the third
one is V Star but this will hold
regardless of which three points I
pick
okay so here is the tricky thing I want
you to look at
so let's look at L
Pi say I want L pi to act on VN +
one right I want L pi to act on VN +
one right so what will be L Pi acting on
vn+ one
huh what is it it's a space of
only space of what is thec space
of of what
l l Pi is the operator corresponding to
the bman equation for pi
right start off by I said last class you
left off by saying L Pi is a contraction
so that L
Pi so L Pi is just a bman bin equation
operating on VN + one so what would that
be
it'll be
this
right this but instead of AR Max here
I'll have a summation over a p s
a I'll have a summation over a pi is a
but what I have done here Pi itself is
an AR Max a right just one action so if
you remember I told you about the
deterministic policies right so this
whole thing will go I'll just replace
this with my p s this will be expected
value of R given s comma Pi s
probability of S Prime given s comma p s
VN + 1 S Prime so that will essentially
be
the L Pi acting on VN + one right is it
is is it
clear
this is l p on VN
+1 I just read it out I just writing
down as aonic expected value of R given
s comma P s+ GMA * summation / S Prime
probability of S Prime given s comma p s
into 2 VN + 1 of S
Prime okay great so now the thing that
you have to
notice how did I get to this
P by
using Max Max I used the max operator
over this right so if I had done L on BN
+
one what would I have
obtained
L on VN + one is essentially this
right Max right this is this is one this
one L on VN + one is essentially this
right so what I have done
here because I chose my pi to be the
max action here so whether I apply L Pi
on vn+ 1 or whether I apply L on vn+ 1
it's the
same because the pi was chosen to be the
max action right so I can say that this
is equal
to sorry not
equalent so the two are
equal
okay okay that makes it easier now we
are going to start simplifying stuffs
okay I'm going to take this expression
I'm going to try and simplify
that
okay why can I can replace V Pi with L
Pi V
Pi
no
why P Pi is a fixed point so nothing
will change I can just replace it l v so
now
so can I do
this same same application of the
triangle inequality as we had before so
the three points
are L Pi V Pi VN + 1 and L VN + 1 so L
VN +1 is just another point in
space right so between three points I
can write
this triangle inequality so this is less
than or equal to actually this is equal
to right so this is the reduction we
talked about here so from LV I went to L
Pi L LVN + one I went to L Pi VN + 1 and
from VN + 1 I went to L VN because that
is how VN plus1 was generated by
applying L
on VN okay so I written that now I can
simplify
this
so I have V Pi n + 1 here V Pi minus VN
+ 1 here sorry and V Pi minus VN + 1
here so I can take it to that side
simplify things so I essentially
[Music]
get
okay that's just the first term now we
have to simplify the second
term
so what's the second
and just like we did earlier I've done a
repeated application of the triangle
inequality right only tricky thing here
is the summation goes Infinity because
only when I repeat this Infinity I'll go
to V
Star right but that's
fine because this is anyway it's a
Vanishing quantity as we go along right
so this some this Su some will actually
exist
[Music]
okay
limit
ofation
yeah well I'm you can think of this as V
Star minus VN + 1
right because I'm just talking about the
norm right so it's V Star minus VN + 1
and then I written this out okay so this
is VN + 1 that's VN + 2 then vn+ 2 VN +
3 blah blah blah so on so
forth so what will this
be you only said it be limit of a
summation right 1 by 1-
G uh GMA G 1us GMA
G yes I need to take one gamma
out okay so what do we have so we have
the first
component is less than or equal to GMA
by 1 - GMA into VN + 1 -
VN right but when three holds what is VN
+ 1 minus VN
epon Epsilon into 1us GMA by 2 GMA right
so if I plug that in what will I
get Epsilon by 2 I plug it in there what
will I get Epsilon by 2 so I have two
components there so V Pi minus V St is
less than or equal to Epsilon by 2 +
Epsilon by 2 which is
Epsilon right V Pius V St is less than
or equal
to okay well you have to actually to
complete the proof you have to do that
uh but I'm asking you to do
that okay so what is the other thing
that we wanted to
show
D already done right so D essentially
was to show that vn+ one will be at
least Epsilon by 2 close so we already
done so we substitute that here so we
get Epsilon by 2 so so VN minus sorry VN
+ 1us V St is less than Epsilon by 2 and
what we are showing there is V Pi minus
V St is less than or equal to Epsilon
Epsilon okay so that's basically done so
we are shown this theorem uh so
essentially what we have here is
that value
iteration
converges with that stopping Criterion
it converges to a Epsilon optimal policy
so you have to pick an Epsilon first
remember gamma comes as part of the
problem definition so once you pick an
Epsilon you can find a stopping
Criterion using that uh expression there
and you're all set okay so there's one
other very interesting thing that people
talk about uh from a theoretical
analysis of algorithms for solving uh
these kinds of uh mdps right so it's
called the rate of convergence so I've
shown you that it converges but there's
this whole concept called rate of
convergence right how quickly does it
approach right so I'm not going to get
into a huge discussions on rate of
convergence and like I mentioned with
the
deterministic policy thing I'll actually
put up a small write up on rate of
convergence as well you can read it uh
one thing which I want to tell you is
that
um so uh you can with a little bit of
not not not much right so L is a
contraction mapping right L is a
contraction so at every
iteration right so my
uh so what is the contraction factor for
L we did this gamma right so for every
iteration I can show that my uh iterates
that is basically I start off with v KN
then I take V1 then V2 V3 and so on so
forth every iteration I can show that
the successive iterates will become
gamma closer
to V Star right so I have some so so V1
was some X close to V Star then V2 will
be gamma X closer to V St so if GMA is
small F it'll converge faster if GMA is
very large it'll converge slower right
so this is called linear convergence
with the rate of
gamma
right so if it falls as gamma
squared then it will be quadratic
convergence right so but linear
convergence with the rate of GMA so this
is essentially the thing so the
interesting aspects I mean if you want
to get into the more into the theory of
all of these things is to start studying
the rates of convergence of different
algorithms and so on so forth which I'm
not going to get into but there
something for as an asside so that you
can look at
[Music]
[Applause]
it